Welcome back. Earlier,
you learned how
your approach can impact
your ability to influence others.
But influencing is about more
than just your approach.
In fact, so much of your
ability to influence
others comes from your
own sources of power.
Throughout your career, you'll
rely on your sources of power to
influence others to do
great work in service
of the project goals.
In his book, The Elements of
Power: Lessons On
Leadership and Influence,
the researcher Terry Bacon
determined that most
power sources fall into
two buckets: organizational
and personal.
From these power sources,
we picked out the
ones we feel are
most important to cover here.
Let's start with organizational
sources of power,
which include your role,
information, network,
and reputation.
First we have your role,
which refers to your position
within an organization or team.
In a project management role,
you have a certain level
of power over the project,
and therefore more influence.
Information is another source
of organizational power,
which refers to your
level of access
and control over information.
As a project manager,
you possess a huge amount of
information about your work
and your stakeholders, which
can work to your benefit.
Now it may be tempting to
assume that as a leader
you have all of the answers,
but to be a good influencer
you should ask questions
and consider all ideas.
You may even hear new insights
and notice issues
in a different way.
Share information with
your team regularly so
that they can provide
input on the full picture.
You can also derive
power from your network.
This refers to people
you're connected
with professionally
and personally.
Strong connections within
your organization and
beyond it can boost your
ability to influence others
and help your
project continue on.
If you demonstrate that
you're well-connected and
have a good chance of getting
stakeholders support
or budget approval
for your plans,
then you're more likely to get
your audience on your side.
You should use your
network to help
colleagues make new connections.
Your team's effectiveness
will increase as you take on
the responsibility of
helping each person
develop their skills and
expand their network,
which in turn increases
their own influencing power.
Lastly, we have reputation,
which refers to how others
perceive you overall.
As you might expect,
people with positive
reputations tend to be more
influential than those
with negative reputations.
One way I've noticed this play
out is through collaboration.
If you're a good collaborator,
you can boost your reputation by
becoming known for being
easy to work with,
keeping your commitments, and
helping others achieve
their own goals.
Your role, access to and control
of information, network,
and reputation are important
organizational sources
of power to be aware of.
It's also important to identify
power sources that come from you.
These are referred to as
personal sources of power,
which include knowledge,
expressiveness,
history, and character.
I like to think of these as
your own personal superpowers.
Knowledge refers to the
power that you draw
from your expertise
in certain subjects,
your unique abilities
and skill sets,
and even your ability
to learn new things.
What comes to mind when you think
about an influential leader?
Typically, they have
a lot of knowledge in
their field and you're more
likely to trust their opinion.
When you're
considering how to use
your own knowledge as
a source of power,
reflect on the expertise
you already have,
and consider areas where you
still want to grow
and learn more.
Expressiveness refers
to your ability
to communicate with others.
This is a big one.
As you learned earlier,
so much of influencing comes
down to how you
approach your audience.
Maybe you're a great storyteller,
or maybe you're really good at
connecting emotionally
with people.
Strong communication
skills like these can
significantly increase your
ability to influence others.
The next personal source
of power is history.
History refers to the level
of personal history there
is between yourself and
another person. Makes sense, right?
A strong relationship with
the person you hope to
influence can go a long way.
As a project manager,
you'll be managing team dynamics
and building team relationships,
which can help you build up
personal history with
the people around
you. And finally, character.
Character refers to
other people's view
of the qualities that make you,
you. Like, honesty, integrity,
kindness, and so much more.
Character is a huge one.
You'll derive an
enormous amount of
power from high estimates
of your character.
What personal characteristics do
you value within yourself?
These are the qualities that have
the power to make you a strong,
supportive leader for
the people around you.
Knowledge, expressiveness,
history, and character
are just four personal
sources of power,
but it's important
to remember that
there's so much wrapped
in each one of these.
There's trustworthiness,
authenticity, wisdom,
and on and on.
There's so many attributes
to draw power from.
I like to think of these elements
as personal superpowers.
I learned early on
in my career that
my personal superpower
is knowledge,
specifically my innate curiosity.
When I started at Google,
I didn't have a background
in software engineering,
but I'm a naturally
curious person
and I'm not afraid
to ask questions.
When I join a new team,
I find the engineer
who seems to have
the most knowledge or experience,
and I ask them to teach
me how everything works.
Most people are genuinely
interested in sharing
what they know.
That initial chat usually
leads to conversations
over lunch,
which helps me to build
my own knowledge
and personal history
with my colleague.
And through these
conversations, I learn
about other teammates
to connect with,
which increases my network.
As you build your career,
try to identify your
own superpowers.
Find the combination of
influencing techniques
that best suits your
particular circumstances.
It takes practice to
polish your skills
and lean into various superpowers
when working with others.
But if you invest
time in thinking
and troubleshooting your
influencing strategy,
it will pay off.
In the next video,
we'll review and wrap
up. Meet you there.